Sherwood Farm Papers, 1845-1930
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Sherwood Farm Papers, 1845-1930
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
100
1 box (0.5 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Joyce Wilkinson from Sherwood Hall Farm, 1981.
Biographical/Historical Information
The history of Sherwood Farm, which served as an ad hoc Quaker Community Archives, began in 1858, when one hundred acres of land north of the Accotink Turnpike was purchased by Charles Ballinger, a Quaker. He married Maria Gibbs and built a house on the acreage in 1859. Seven years later, he purchased an additional hundred acres of land south of the Accotink Turnpike. This two hundred acre spread comprised Sherwood Farm, which belonged to the Ballinger/Wilkinson families for five generations. Mary Alice Ballinger was born there in 1866. She married Francis H. Wilkinson, also a Quaker, who was a son of Morris R. Wilkinson and Sarah Kirk Wilkinson of Gray's Hill Farm, in 1891.
Scope and Content
The Wilkinson Family papers consist of Sarah Kirk Wilkinson's day books, a few of her son Francis' school papers, and assorted Wilkinson correspondence. There are also two diaries from Unionville, Pennsylvania, unsigned, which most likely belonged to Quaker relatives. The Sherwood Farm papers include: Woodlawn Farmer's Club correspondence, describing various social activities of the Quaker farmers and their families from the area; Woodlawn Horse Company correspondence, which includes the constitution and by-laws of this anti-horse theft organization; Woodlawn Housekeeping Association correspondence, constitution, by-laws and minutes; records from the Woodlawn Literary Association; Sherwood Hall Sunday School records; and blank Sherwood Farm Dairy Records showing how the milk production was recorded and sold from 1918-1940. There is also a newspaper article from the Sunday Star in 1905, describing Quaker families and history in this area.
Arrangement
By subject: therein chronologically. Series 1 is the Wilkinson Family Papers; Series 2 is the Sherwood Farm Papers.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
The original records of the Woodlawn Housekeeping Association, the Sherwood Hall Sunday School, and the Woodlawn Literary Association are in the Virginia Room of the Fairfax City Regional Library. This manuscript collection contains photocopies of all of the above mentioned records.
Related Material
Reminiscences of Sherwood Farm and the Surrounding Area by Charles Kirk Wilkinson, Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook.
The Woodlawn Agricultural Society Records, 1866-1903, microfilm 00435.
The Woodlawn Housekeeping Association Records, microfilm 00435.
Index Terms
Ballinger family; Dairy farms--Virginia--Fairfax County; Quakers--Virginia--Fairfax County; Wilkinson family
Contents List
- Wilkinson Family Papers (Box-folder 100: 1-6)
  - Sarah Kirk Wilkinson day books, 1839-1845. (Box-folder 100:1)
  - Diary, Unionville, PA, 1873. (Box-folder 100:2)
  - Francis Wilkinson school papers, 1881-1883. (Box-folder 100:3)
  - Diary, Unionville, PA, 1881-1884. (Box-folder 100:4)
  - Wilkinson correspondence, undated. (Box-folder 100:5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated. (Box-folder 100:6)
- Sherwood Farm Papers (Box-folder 100: 7-17)
  - Woodlawn Farmer's Club correspondence, 1902-1906. (Box-folder 100:7)
  - Quakers of Mount Vernon, The Sunday Star, 1905. (Box-folder 100:8)
  - Woodlawn Horse Company, 1908. (Box-folder 100:9)
  - Travel literature, 1930. (Box-folder 100:10)
  - Sherwood Farm Dairy record cards, undated. (Box-folder 100:11)
  - Woodlawn Housekeeping Association correspondence, 1876-1891. (Box-folder 100:12)
  - Woodlawn Housekeeping Association constitution, 1876-1896. (Box-folder 100:13)
  - Woodlawn Housekeeper's Society minutes, 1886-1896. (Box-folder 100:14)
  - Woodlawn Housekeeper's Society by-laws and minutes, 1891-1896. (Box-folder 100:15)
  - Woodlawn Literary Association records, 1902. (Box-folder 100:16)
  - Sherwood Hall Sunday School records, 1901-1905. (Box-folder 100:17)